REPO TEST Finding Aid to the National Commission on Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome Records, 1983-1994
History of Medicine Division, National Library of Medicine.
REPO TEST National Commission on Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome Records 1983-1994
United States. National Commission on Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome
10.2 linear feet (8 boxes)
MS C 544
Materials stored onsite. History of Medicine Division. National Library of Medicine
Briefing books, hearing and meeting transcripts, reports, and press clippings document the activities of the National Commission on Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome. Materials cover all but the last year of the Commission's existence. The majority of the collection consists of briefing books, and hearing and meeting transcripts of the National Commission.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions on access.
Commission Members List
June E. Osborn, M.D., Chairman
David E. Rogers, M.D., Vice Chairman
The Honorable Diane Ahrens
K. Scott Allen
Don C. Des Jarlais, Ph.D.
Eunice Diaz, M.S., M.P.H.
Mary D. Fisher
Donald S. Goldman, Esq.
Larry Kessler
Charles Konigsberg, Jr. M.D., M.P.H.
The Honorable J. Roy Rowland, M.D.
Ex Officio
Les Aspin, Ph. D., Secretary of Defense
Donna E Shalala, Secretary of Health and Human Services
Jesse Brown, Secretary of Veterans Affairs
Department of Defense
Col. Michael R. Peterson, D.V.M., Dr. P.H., Executive Secretary, Armed Forces Epidemiological Board
Department of Health and Human Services National AIDS Program Office
James R. Allen, M.D., M.P.H., Former Director
Valerie Setlow, Ph.D., Acting Director
Department of Veterans Affairs
Irwin Pernick, J.D., Former Counselor to the Secretary, Associated Deputy Assistant for Policy
Marvelu R. Peterson, Ph.D., Associate Director, AIDS Services
Former Members
Harlon L. Dalton, Esq.
Earvin Johnson, Jr.
Belinda Mason
Richard B. Cheney, Former Secretary of Defense
Edward J. Derwinski, M.D., Former Secretary of Veterans Affairs
Louis W. Sullivan, M.D., Former Secretary of Health and Human Services
Historical Note
The National Commission on Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome was an independent body created in 1989 by federal statute (Public Law 100-607). The mission of the National Commission was to advise Congress and the President on the development of "a consistent national policy" concerning the HIV epidemic. The statute created the Commission for a period of up to four years, which expired on September 3, 1993.
The National Commission was preceded by the Presidential Commission on the Human Immunodeficiency Virus Epidemic, which was established on June 24, 1987, by Executive Order 12601. The Presidential Commission held over 45 days of hearings and site visits in preparation of their final report to the President, which was completed on June 27, 1988. One of the recommendations of the final report was the development of a national commission on AIDS to continue their work.
The National Commission consisted of fifteen members including five appointed by the Senate; five by the House; two by President George W. Bush Sr.; and the secretaries of Health and Human Services, Defense, and the Veterans Administration. The Commission accomplished its mission through numerous hearings and site visits.
The Commission's hearings covered the following topic concerning AIDS: healthcare, treatment, and international aspects of the HIV epidemic; Federal, State, and Local responsibilities; the Southern California epidemic; social and human issues; Executive and Legislative branch issues; current research and clinical trials; HIV epidemic in the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico; African American communities; Pediatric and Adolescent HIV; Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual communities among Asians, Asian Americans, and Pacific Islanders; Women and HIV disease and civil rights; religious communities response; and risks of transmission in healthcare settings.
Site visits included Southern California community based organizations in order to observe their response to the epidemic. Other site visits also included the homeless in New York City, Newark, and Jersey City; AIDS in the rural communities of Waycross, Albany, and Macon, Georgia; HIV and AIDS in New York City correctional facilities; the epidemic in the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico; regional responses in Belle Glade and Miami, Florida; and the Native American Communities of Oklahoma, Minnesota, South Dakota, Arizona, and New Mexico.
During its tenure the Commission produced fifteen reports plus analytical and policy statements on a number of issues. AIDS: An Expanding Tragedy, the Commission's final report was issued in June 1993. The final report discusses the future of the AIDS epidemic in America and established two main recommendations on the appropriate response. The first recommendation was that leaders at all levels must speak out about AIDS to their constituencies. Secondly, we must develop a clear well-articulated national plan for confronting AIDS. The steps necessary to meet these guidelines are outlined by the Commission in Mobilizing America's Response to AIDS, which was sent directly to the President.
Collection Summary
Briefing books, hearing and meeting transcripts, reports, and press clippings (1983-1993; 10.2 l.f.) document the activities of the National Commission on Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (NCAIDS). Materials cover all but the last year of the Commission's existence. The majority of the collection consists of NCAIDS briefing books, and hearing and meeting transcripts. Series I contains hearing transcripts from the Commission's predecessor, the Presidential Commission on the Human Immunodeficiency Virus Epidemic (1987-1988); Series II contains the work conducted by NCAIDS. In Series III the collection also includes various topical reports on AIDS published by external agencies. There are no notes or correspondence in this collection and all materials appear here in published form. In addition, the Commission's report Mobilizing America's Response to AIDS, is also not included within this collection but can be found n the Library's General Collection. The bulk of the collection spans the years 1987 to early 1992.
The collection comprises four series: Presidential Commission on the Human Immunodeficiency Virus Epidemic, 1987-1988; Briefings and Transcripts of Hearings and Meetings, 1989-1992; Press Coverage and Reports, 1989-1993; and Reports on AIDS from External Institutions and Government Agencies, 1983-1992.
Of special interest is the Commission's final report AIDS: An Expanding Tragedy, which serves as a summary of the Commission's activities and includes a detailed chronology of its activities and provides an extensive list of all hearings, site visits, reports, and publications related to the Commission.
Index Terms
These terms are indexed in the National Library of Medicine's online catalog LocatorPlus. Researchers wishing to find related materials should search the catalog using these terms.
MESH Subjects
Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome; African Americans; Homosexuality; Human Immunodeficiency Virus; Public Health
Corporate Names
United States. Presidential Commission on the Human Immunodeficiency Virus Epidemic
Series Descriptions
- Series I: Presidential Commission On The Human Immunodeficiency Virus Epidemic, 1987-1988, 101083016Y1
  This series contains transcripts of hearings and two reports from the first instance of the commission. The hearing transcripts cover topics such as IV drug abuse, social, legal, financial, ethical, and safety issues concerning AIDS.
  Provenance
  Gift, John L. Parascandola, PHS Historian's Office, 3/1/1994, Acc. #812. Gift, Donald Goldman, Acc. #2005-21.
  - Hearing Transcripts, 101083016Y2
    - Congressional, Sept. 30, 1987, 101083016X3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Hearing, Nov. 24, 1987, 101083016X4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - IV Drug Abuse and HIV, Dec. 17-18, 1987, 101083016X5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Care of HIV Infected Persons, Jan. 13-15, 1988, 101083016X6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Research, Feb. 18-20, 1988, 101083016X7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Interim Report Executive Session, Feb. 29, Mar. 3, 1988, 101083016X8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Prevention and Education, Mar. 1-3, 1988, 101083016X9 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Discrimination, Ethics, and Testing, Mar. 16-18, 1988, 101083016X10 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - Western States Response, Mar. 24-25, 1988, 101083016X11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Uniform Crime Reporting [U.S. Department of Justice], 1988 (Box 8, Folder 31)